A Guide to the Papers of James Lawrence Basil Williams ca. 1895-1995
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Lawrence Basil Williams ca. 1895-1995
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11206
There are ca. 10,800 items.
This collection consists of ca. 10,800 items, ca. 1895-1995, pertaining to James Lawrence Basil Williams, his religious career, and his family. Included are correspondence, papers, printed material, photographs, manuscripts, diplomas, and memorabilia. There is substantial material concerning Williams' clerical activities at various American churches and parishes as well as overseas. The majority of this material may be found under "Bethesda by-the-Sea" and "Church?"; there is also related religious material under "American Center for Theological Studies," "Diocese of Virginia," "Ordination?" and other specific categories in the "Alphabetical/Topical" series. There are papers related to religious associations and congregations and historical societies, Williams' naval career, and the Williams' family home, "Upshot," Boyce, Virginia. Prominent correspondents in "Autographs" include Lloyd Millard Bentsen; Harry Flood Byrd; Harry Flood Byrd, Jr.; Hubert Horatio Humphrey; Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.; Frederick William Neve; Prince Louis H. M. Bertrand Rainier III; Princess Grace of Monaco; Harry S. Truman; and, Thornton (Niven) Wilder. There is also a letter, May 20, 1937, from Cordell Hull, concerning "Alexis Sommaripa."
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was made a gift to the Library by James Lawrence Basil Williams of "Huntlands," Middleburg, Virginia, on September 20, 1995. There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Lawrence Basil Williams (March 1, 1914- ) was born in Colonial Beach, Virginia to Hiram Walter Basil and Clara (Denmead) Williams. He obtained his undergraduate and graduate education at Randolph-Macon Academy, Randolph-Macon College, and the University of Virginia. He later studied at the University of Minnesota, the Virginia Theological Seminary, Frederick Wilhelm University in Bonn, Germany, American University, American Bible Institute in Kansas City, Missouri, and New York University. Williams was minister-in-charge at Immanuel Church-on-the-Hill, Virginia Theological Seminary, in Alexandria, Virginia, 1947- 1953; minister of Henry Stimson Chapel in Bad Godesberg, Germany, 1953-1954; rector at Cunningham Chapel Parish in Millwood, Virginia, 1954-1958, Grace Parish, Oklahoma, 1958, St. Basil Church in Tahlequah, Oklahoma, Bethesda by-the-Sea in Palm Beach, Florida; associate rector at St. Thomas Church in New York City, Church of Holy Spirit in Nice, France; and founder and dean of the American Center for Theological Studies in Boyce, Virginia, 1958--.
Other activities and memberships included thoroughbred bloodstock agent, Stallion Service, Inc.; chairman, White House Conference Committee on Aging, Oklahoma, 1960; member, Bishop and Council Diocese of Oklahoma, Ecumenical Commission, Episcopal Church, 1960; board member, Overseas Mission Society, Bethel Memorial Association, James Monroe Birthplace Association; served from ensign to lieutenant commander in the United States Naval Reserve, 1941-1947; member, Society of Cincinnati, Sons of the Revolution, Society of Colonial Wars, Order Lafayette, Chaplain Flag Institute, Welsh-American Society, Society of the Descendants of Colonial Clergy, Brecknock Society, National Trust Historical Preservation, Virginia Breeders Association, Sertoma, Ruritan, American Legion, Phi Delta Theta, Alpha Kappa Psi, and Sigma Upsilon. Williams was also a member of the following clubs: Chevy Chase; Metropolitan; Army-Navy-Country (Boyce, Virginia); and, American (Nice, France). Authored works include An Economic and Social Survey of Westmoreland County, Virginia, 1935; Minister without Portfolio, 1954; Contemporary Virginia, and Williams of Upshot in Virginia, 1613-1976. He also produced two television documentaries, This World and the Next and A Dead Certainty. [ Who's Who in the South and Southeast, 1973-1974 edition, F208.W64].
Lawrence Williams married Jean Rowell McCardell (October 1, 1905 ? January 16, 1977) on September 13, 1941, and had children Judith Lawrence Barcroft Williams, who married Wisner Washam, and Ian Rowell Denmead Williams, who married Debora Anne Wornom. Grandchildren are Amy Lawrence Washam, Ian Miller Washam, Aubrey Lee Williams, and Ashton Boyce Denmead Williams. Jean Rowell McCardell Williams was the daughter of Wilfred S. McCardell and Annabelle Rowell. Jean Williams was a direct descendant of Captain Peter Humrickhouse of the Philadelphia Regiment who served in the Revolution and as a special aide to General George Washington. She was a granddaughter of Ambrose E. Rowell of Falls Church and was the first granddaughter of the Princeton University Class of 1877. Mrs. Williams was educated at Western High School and Wilson Teachers College in Washington and the University of Maryland. She was active in social service organizations. In the 1930s, she served as chairman of the curriculum committee and textbook committees of the District of Columbia school system and was a demonstration teacher at Brightwood School. She also served as a fashion consultant in New York and a wedding consultant for the Old Tailored Woman shop on Fifth Street. After her marriage to Reverend Williams, she became active in church social work and helped her husband establish new parishes, including Episcopal parishes in Millwood, Virginia and among Indians in Muskogee, Oklahoma. She was also active in church work in Alexandria; Bonn, Germany; Palm Beach, Florida; Nice, France; Rome, Italy; London, England, and Geneva, Switzerland. While in France, she founded the Woman?s Club of the Riviera and was named Woman of the Year in 1970 by the organization. In 1970, Princess Grace of Monaco presented her with a medallion honoring her hospitality work with American Servicemen in the Sixth Fleet and with tourists and international students there. [obituaries, 1977, in collection]
Jean Williams passed away in January 1977; Lawrence Williams was remarried to Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham (January 6, 1915 ? September 30, 1994) on August 27, 1977. She had a daughter, Camilla Cooper Hewitt. Griselda Williams was the daughter of international banker, Francis Lee Higginson and Mehitable Coolidge Sargent. She was the great, great, great granddaughter of Thomas Jefferson and a descendant of Pocahontas. She was educated at the Winsor School in Boston and subsequently studied in Paris and at Columbia University in New York. During her first marriage to Abram Hewitt, she became involved in the thoroughbred horse industry and was later active in the shorthorn cattle business at their plantation, "Montana Hall" in White Post, Virginia. She was especially active in the work of 4-H Clubs and was honored by the Virginia Polytechnic Institute for her work and support. She served as a member of the 4-H Center near Front Royal, Virginia, and was board member of the Grafton School for students with special needs, as well as a charter member of the Friends of Blandy, Virginia State Arboretum. Her philanthropies centered on education for minorities, particularly African-Americans and Native Americans. She was also a member of the Chilton Club in Boston and of the Royal Society of Saint George. A lifelong Episcopalian, Mrs. Williams assisted her husband as chaplain to Sicily, being active in the Anglican communities of Palermo and Taormina; in Oslo, Norway and at Gustavia, Saint Barthelemy in the Antilles. [memorials, 1994, in collection]
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 10,800 items, ca. 1895-1995, pertaining to James Lawrence Basil Williams, his religious career, and his family. Included are correspondence, papers, printed material, photographs, manuscripts, diplomas, and memorabilia. There is substantial material concerning Williams' clerical activities at various American churches and parishes as well as overseas. The majority of this material may be found under "Bethesda by-the-Sea" and "Church?"; there is also related religious material under "American Center for Theological Studies," "Diocese of Virginia," "Ordination?" and other specific categories in the "Alphabetical/Topical" series. There are papers related to religious associations and congregations and historical societies, Williams' naval career, and the Williams' family home, "Upshot," Boyce, Virginia. Prominent correspondents in "Autographs" include Lloyd Millard Bentsen; Harry Flood Byrd; Harry Flood Byrd, Jr.; Hubert Horatio Humphrey; Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.; Frederick William Neve; Prince Louis H. M. Bertrand Rainier III; Princess Grace of Monaco; Harry S. Truman; and, Thornton (Niven) Wilder. There is also a letter, May 20, 1937, from Cordell Hull, concerning "Alexis Sommaripa."
Represented among the "Family Correspondence and Papers" are Judith Barcroft Williams Washam (July 6, 1942--), her husband Wisner M. Washam, and their children, Amy Lawrence and Ian Miller; Ian Rowell Denmead Williams, his wife Deborah Anne (Wornom), and their children Anne McCardell, and Ashton Boyce Denmead. Papers of Judith Barcroft and Wisner Washam pertain chiefly to personal matters but also refer to her acting career in theatre and daytime television, and his writing career in daytime television, including All My Children and Guiding Light. Among the family papers, there are personal letters, schools papers, printed material, children's drawings and photographs. There are also papers of Williams' parents, Hiram Walter Basil Williams and Clara Lipscomb (Denmead), including correspondence and printed material. In addition to some photographs contained in individuals' folders, there is a separate folder of photographs at the end of the series.
Other series in this collection are: "Papers of Jean Rowell McCardell Williams" and "Papers of Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham Williams." Jean Williams' papers consist chiefly of correspondence with Lawrence Williams. There is also material concerning her illness and death. Griselda Williams' papers include letters to her father while studying in Paris, France and traveling abroad, papers from her marriages to Abram Hewitt and Robert N. Cunningham, and papers re her marriage to Lawrence Williams and her death. There are correspondence, papers, legal papers, printed material, and photographs concerning Jean Williams and Griselda Williams.
Contents List
- Alphabetical/Topical 1935-1995 (Box 1-12)
  - "A" Miscellaneous 1959-1982 (Box 1)
  - American Bible Institute 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Center for Theological Studies, Inc. 1959-1986, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Appointment Calendar 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Armed Forces Commission in cooperation with the Diocesan Commission 1952-1972 (Box 2)
  - Brian Ashen 1971-1991, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Association of International Churches Europe and Middle East 1971-1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Autographs 1935-1991 (Box 2)
    Among the correspondents are: Sherman Adams (1899-1986); Lloyd Millard Bentsen (1921- ); Ralph Johnson Bunche (1904-1971); Harry Flood Byrd (1877-1966); Harry Flood Byrd, Jr. (1914- ); James Harold Doolittle (1896-1993); Hubert Horatio Humphrey (1911-1978); Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr. (1902-1985); Frederick William Neve (1855-1948); Prince Louis H. M. Bertrand Renier III (1923- ); Princess Grace of Monaco (1929-1982); Harry S. Truman (1884-1972); and Thronton (Niven) Wilder) (1897-1975).
  - "B" Miscellaneous 1963-1994 (Box 3)
  - Nicholas Bamburac 1971-1973 (Box 3)
  - Bethesda-by-the-Sea 1959-1979, n.d., 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Bethesda-By-The-Sea: Chronicles 1889-19641964 (Box 3)
  - Bethesda Affair Testimonials 1964-1973 (Box 3)
  - Birthday Cards 1988-1995 (Box 3)
  - Blandy Experimental Farm 1990-1994 (Box 4)
  - Blue Ridge Hunt 1982-1984 (Box 4)
  - A. Smith Bowman, Jr. 1952-1975 (Box 4)
  - Frances Rosser Brown 1961-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - "C" Miscellaneous 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - John Martin Cates, Jr. 1969-1993 (Box 4)
  - Owen Robertson Cheatham 1964-1975 (Box 4)
  - Christopher T. Chenery 1961-1973 (Box 4)
  - Chevy Chase Club 1957-1970 (Box 4)
  - Church--American Church of the Holy Spirit, Nice, France 1964-1974 (Box 4)
  - Church--Church of England 1966-1988 (Box 4)
  - Church--Cunningham Chapel Parish, Millwood, Virginia 1954-1979 (Box 4)
  - Church--Grace Episcopal Parish, Muskogee, Oklahoma 1958-1961 (Box 4)
  - Church--Miscellaneous 1973-1995 (Box 4)
  - Church--Music 1946-1968 (Box 4)
  - Church--St. Barthelemey, Gustavia, French Antilles 1983 (Box 5)
  - Church--St. Mary's Episcopal Church, Colonial Beach, Virginia 1963-1983 (Box 5)
  - Church--St. Paul's Within the Walls, Rome, Italy 1956-1961 (Box 5)
  - Chruch--St. Thomas Church, New York, New York 1966-1974 (Box 5)
  - Church--Stimson Memorial Chapel, Bonn, Germany 1953-1958 (Box 5)
  - Civil Service Commission Application 1965 (Box 5)
  - Clarke County, Virginia Sequicentennial 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Clevedon Civic Society 1992-1995 (Box 5)
  - Harry T. Cleven 1982-1985 (Box 5)
  - Morgan L. Combs, Jr. 1942 (Box 5)
  - Convocation of American Churches in Europe Episcopal 1971-1984, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Convocation of American Churches in Europe: Directories 1973-1975 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae--Clergy Deployment 1969-1972 (Box 5)
  - Treadwell Davison 1941-1971 (Box 5)
  - "Denmead Farm," Monroe Hall, Westmoreland County, Virginia 1971-1978 (Box 5)
  - Diocese of Virginia 1973-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Diuguid family 1950, 1985-1995 (Box 6)
  - Doctorate of Divinity 1964-1971 (Box 6)
  - "Duxbury," Plymouth County, Massachussetts 1953-1959 (Box 6)
  - Education--James Lawrence Basil Williams 1933-1971 (Box 6)
  - Helen Elliott 1986-1988 (Box 6)
  - Viola Ellison 1984-1989 (Box 6)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Blanche Fields 1944-1965 (Box 6)
  - Dorey Fisher 1946 (Box 6)
  - Allen Fore 1982-1992 (Box 6)
  - "G" Miscellaneous 1964-1983 (Box 6)
  - Ted Gardner 1972 (Box 6)
  - Gibraltar in Europe: John R. Satterthwaite 1970-1990 (Box 6)
  - Gibraltar in Europe Diocesan Gazette 1971, 1981-1990 (Box 6)
  - Robert F. Gibson, Jr. 1945-1973 (Box 7)
  - Sidney Wilmot Goldsmith, Jr. 1948-1971 (Box 7)
  - Frederick Deane Goodwin 1945-1971 (Box 7)
  - Gray Commission--Opposition 1955-1956 (Box 7)
  - Robert E. Gribben 1946-1948 (Box 7)
  - Jean Guepin (Lady Broughan and Vaux) 1977 (Box 7)
  - "H" Miscellaneous 1941-1992 (Box 7)
  - Richard R. Harshman--Limericks and miscellaneous 1984-1990 (Box 7)
  - Richard R. Harshman and family 1983-1994 (Box 7)
  - Sir Charles and Lady Susan Anthea Hodson 1947-1984 (Box 7)
  - Christopher Hodson 1986-1992 (Box 7)
  - Horse Industry: Ministry 1971-1973 (Box 8)
  - Horse Industry: Pari-Mutuel 1972 (Box 8)
  - Horse Industry: Racing 1948-1973, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Olive Hughes 1985-1994 (Box 8)
  - "K & L" Miscellaneous 1962-1982 (Box 8)
  - Commander Willam T. Kirk, III 1946 (Box 8)
  - Edith Montgomery Lee (Mrs. Walter Lee) 1956-1961 (Box 8)
  - Thomas G. Lyttelton 1982-1994 (Box 8)
  - "M" Miscellaneous 1956-1982 (Box 8)
  - Patrick A. C. Madden 1981-1992 (Box 8)
  - Marriages 1947, 1971-1985 (Box 8)
  - William F. Micklem 1986, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Middleburg Players Bicentennial--Presentation of 1776 1976 (Box 9)
  - Monroe Birthplace Association, Monroe Hall, Virginia 1951-1974 (Box 9)
  - "N & O & R" Miscellaneous 1942-1950 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Hospitalization Record 1944-1946 (Box 9)
  - Navy-Medical 1967 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Miscellaneous 1942-1969 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Navigation (V-1, V-7, V-12) 1942-1943 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Personnel 1941-1979 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Personnel 1941-1979 (Box 9)
  - Navy--Supplies and Accounts 1950-1970 (Box 9)
  - "Old Hundred" Paris, Va 1957-1962 (Box 9)
  - Ordination to the Diaconate 1946-1948 (Box 9)
  - Ordination to the Priesthood 1947-1948, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Chilton Powell 1959-1982 (Box 10)
  - Printed re James Lawrence Basil Williams 1937-1974, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Ellen Quinn 1936-1937, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Refugees 1922-1957 (Box 10)
  - "S" Miscellaneous 1950, 1982-1988 (Box 10)
  - Wolter Schopenhauer 1959-1960 (Box 10)
  - William Ewen Shipp Estate 1962-1971 (Box 10)
  - Sicily, Italy 1982 (Box 10)
  - Allen Smith 1988-1994 (Box 10)
  - Society of the Cincinnati 1925-1988, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Society of Colonial Wars 1950-1995, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Society of the Descendants of Colonial Clergy 1966-1990 (Box 11)
  - Alexis Sommaripa 1937-1944 (Box 11)
  - Sons of the Revolution 1952-1995 (Box 11)
  - Nellie Lewis Stafford (Mrs. George Joseph) 1936-1962 (Box 11)
  - Charles B. Sweatt 1956-1973 (Box 11)
  - "T & U" Miscellaneous 1977-1982 (Box 11)
  - Richard Porter Thomsen 1977-1992 (Box 11)
  - George Fabian Tittmann 1978-1979 (Box 11)
  - Joseph B. Tucker 1946-1950 (Box 12)
  - Upshot--Financial and Legal 1956-1979 (Box 11)
  - Upshot--Inventory 1976 (Box 11)
  - Upshot--Remodeling--Exterior and Landscape 1971-1976 (Box 12)
  - Upshot--Remodeling--Interior 1967-1977 (Box 12)
  - "W" Miscellaneous, 1959-1990 (Box 12)
  - A.D. Wilkinson, 1964-1967 (Box 12)
  - Susan Williams, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Williams of Upshot in Virginia 1612-1976, 1977-1991; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Edward M. Wingfield, 1947-1984 (Box 12)
  - Glen G. Wolfe (U.S. Embassy, Paris), 1956-1972 (Box 12)
  - Writings Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 12)
  - "Y" Miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 12)
  - Alexander Clinton Zabriskie, 1946-1959 (Box 12)
- Family Correspondence and Papers, 1942-1995, n.d. (Box 13-15)
  - Amy Lawrence Washam, 1978-1995 (Box 13)
  - Ian Miller Washam, 1982-1995 (Box 13)
  - Judith Barcroft (Williams) Washam, 1942, 1956-1994, n.d.; 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Judith Barcroft (Williams) Washam: Art Exhibits and Theatre Announcements and Programs, 1979-1995 (Box 13)
  - Judith Barcroft (Williams) Washam: Stephens College, 1961-1963 (Box 13)
  - Wisner M. Washam, 1984-1993 (Box 13)
  - Anne McCardell Williams, 1985-1995 (Box 14)
  - Aubrey Lee Williams and Frank S. Williams, 1984-1993 (Box 14)
  - Ashton Boyce Denmead Williams, 1978-1995 (Box 14)
  - Basil Williams, 1906-1923 (Box 14)
  - Clara Lipscomb Denmead Williams, 1930-1947 (Box 14)
  - Clara Lipscomb Denmead Williams, 1958-1965 (Box 14)
  - Debora Anne Wornom Williams, 1961-1994 (Box 14)
  - Hiram Walter Basil Williams, 1895-1961 (Box 14)
  - Ian Rowell Denmead Williams, 1949-1992; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Ian Rowell Denmead Williams: Legal and Political Careers, 1979-1994 (Box 15)
  - Ian Rowell Denmead Williams: School Records, 1954-1974 (Box 15)
  - William Denmead Williams and Mary Lygia Williams, 1935-1982 (Box 15)
  - Williams Family Photographs, 1950s-1980s, n.d. (Box 15)
- Papers of Jean Rowell McCardell Williams, 1935-1978 (Box 16-18)
  - J.L.B. Williams to Jean Rowell McCardell Williams, 1935-1942 (Box 16)
  - J.L.B. Williams to Jean Rowell McCardell Williams, 1944; 4 folders (Box 16)
  - J.L.B. Williams to Jean Rowell McCardell Williams, 1945; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - J.L.B. Williams to Jean Rowell McCardell Williams, 1958-1975 (Box 16)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams to J.L.B. Williams: V-Mail, 1944; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams to J.L.B. Williams, 1945; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams to J.L.B. Williams, 1952-1974 (Box 17)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams: Marriage, 1941 (Box 17)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams: Illness, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams: Illness, 1976-1977 (Box 18)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams: Death, 1977 (Box 18)
  - Jean Rowell McCardell Williams: Condolences, 1977-1978; 4 folders (Box 18)
- Papers of Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham Williams, 1932-1995, n.d. (Box 19-21)
  - Griselda Higginson to Francis Lee Higginson, 1932-1933 (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson to Francis Lee Higginson, 1933 (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson to Francis Lee Higginson, 1933-1936 (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson to Francis Lee Higginson, 1937-1938 (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt: Photographs, 1940s-1950s (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham: Trustee Papers for the Beneficiaries of Marian Appleton Sargent, 1949-1961 (Box 19)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt, 1935-1939 (Box 20)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt, 1940-1949 (Box 20)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1950-1956 (Box 20)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1957 (Box 20)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1958; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1959-1963 (Box 21)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1964-1974; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham, 1965-1974 (Box 21)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham Williams: Marriage, 1977; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham Williams, 1979-1994, n.d.; 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Griselda Higginson Hewitt Cunningham Williams: Memorials, 1994-1995 (Box 21)
- Western High School Diploma for Jean Rowell McCardell, 1923 Jan 31 (Oversize OS Box M-26)
- University of Virginia Diploma for James Lawrence Basil Williams, 1936 Aug 28 (Oversize OS Box M-26)
- University of Virginia Diploma for James Lawrence Basil Williams, 1941 Jun 9 (Oversize OS Box M-26)
- Diocese of Virginia Ordaining James Lawrence Basil Williams as Deacon, 1947 Jun 26 (Oversize OS Box M-26)
- Montana Hall, White Post, Virginia architectural drawing for new windows by Williams R. Huntington, 1956 Nov 11 (Oversize OS Box M-26)
- Montana Hall, White Post, Virginia architectural drawing for kitchen skylight by Williams R. Huntington, 1956 Dec 17 (Oversize OS Box M-26)